<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state of Spaine. Translated out of French</title>
            <title>Estat d'Espagne. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22997</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125625</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898445</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898445</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132660</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73201)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132660)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2050:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state of Spaine. Translated out of French</title>
                  <title>Estat d'Espagne. English.</title>
                  <author>Sergier, Richard, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Lewkenor, Lewis, Sir, d. 1626, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by P. S[hort]. for Richard Serger,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>French original not traced; probably a translation of: L'estat d'Espagne. Avec le proces verbal de l'hommage faict par l'ayeul du roy Philippess .. au roy de France Loys XII., published in the same year in the Low Countries. The translation is sometime attributed to Richard Sergier (who signs dedication) and, less probably, to Sir Lewis Lewkenor.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The state of Spaine.</note>
                  <note>Another issue of STC 22996 with added quires F-G⁴ H² . As *1 of STC 22996, the dedication to R. Sonds, was printed as H2 of STC 22997, it is clear that both "issues" were printed at the same time. Whether the copies of STC 22996 are imperfect or represent a distinct issue is uncertain--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ 2E²  F-G⁴ H²  (H2 = *1 of STC 22996)--STC.</note>
                  <note>reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spain --  History --  Philip II, 1556-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Politics and government --  1556-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:132660:1"/>
                  <p>THE PRESENT ſtate of Spaine. </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tranſlated out of French.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                     <q>ET VSQVE AD NUBES VERITAS TVA</q>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by P. S. for <hi>Richard Serger.</hi> 1594.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:132660:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132660:2"/>
                  <head>THE STATE OF SPAINE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a thing noted from all antiquitie; that God hath appointed in this worlde the certayne continuance of Monarchies, eſtats, and families, hath lymited the proſperity and thraledome of nations, and bounded the very liues of all men liuing: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe as well in matters of ſtate as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate thoſe are founde moſte durable which retayne and keep the greateſt perfection and excellencye from their creator: Some being ordained to ſerue for miniſters of his furie, otherſome for examples of his diuine bounty and grace. For we ſee many men and ſundry eſtates whome God hath from moſte baſe foundations and petty beginninges raiſed and aduaunced to the moſt ſupreame degree of power and dignity, inueſting them with mighty Empires and boundleſſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. With whoſe power as of men little vertuous, it hath pleaſed the almightye to ſerue himſelfe, but as with a ſcourge to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Enormous ſins of his people, others
<pb facs="tcp:132660:3"/>haue beene ratified from God aboue in this moſt ſoueraigne degree of all humaine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty in recompence of their holineſſe of life and vnreprouable dealing among men. But ſo ſoone as the one or the other, beganne to forget the occaſion for which they were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in this world, which was to ſet forth the kingdom, honour and glory of God onely: whome they together with all men ought to confeſſe to be their general Lord and father; and that they haue gonne a boute by falſe pretextes, and ſiniſter meanes to aduaunce their owne priuat honor and glory, and not that of their great Lord and maiſter. Then God who alone raigneth whome onely we oughte to ſerue, caſteth them downe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, deſtroyeth their monarchies, deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth their kingdomes, and rooteth out their poſterity from off the face of the earth.</p>
                  <p>For example the crowne of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, a little country gouerned by Iudges, afterwardes by Earles, in the end by Kings, created through the beneficence of <hi>Samſon,</hi> the fourth of that name King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, <hi>Samſon</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> was by <hi>Jſabel</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped from the daughter of <hi>Henrye</hi> laſte of
<pb facs="tcp:132660:3"/>that name, Kinge of <hi>Caſtile:</hi> the ſaide <hi>Jſabell</hi> matched in mariage with <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> ſonne to king <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Aragon</hi> whoſe kingdoms en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed almoſt in our memory into a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty puiſſaunce and ſtate. But for that the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors therof not reſting content with thoſe blesſings which God hath giuen them here on earth, haue in hoſtile maner inuaded the Countries and poſſesſions of other Princes, they ſeeme at this preſente to menace their own ruine, as I hope to dilate more at large.</p>
                  <p>This Prince then, ambitious, if euer were any in this world, amongſt other his famous feates of Armes, to the ende to inueigle the earle of <hi>Rousſillon,</hi> from <hi>Charles</hi> the eighte king of <hi>France,</hi> made no bones to abandon his owne Couſin Germaine, and brother in law <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> kinge of <hi>Naples</hi> to the furie of thoſe Armies whome <hi>Charles</hi> the eight marched againſt him for the recouery of the ſayd kingdome. Then during the raigne of <hi>Lewes,</hi> the twelfth breaking al conditions of League and amitye, forcing the degree of kindred and alliaunce, which hee had with <hi>Frederick</hi> then king of <hi>Naples,</hi> he confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with king <hi>Lewes</hi> to diſpoſſeſſe <hi>Frederick</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:132660:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> and to ſhare it betweene them two (as in effecte they did.) Afterwarde vnder a collour of ſupporting <hi>Pope Julius</hi> the ſecond, his quarrell againſte the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> and the kinge of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> but of a troth for very feare he had of the greatnes of our king, who then might haue chaſed him eaſely out of his vniuſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, which he held in Italie: he entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>Pope</hi> in deadly grudge againſte him, and ſtirred vp the king of Englande and the Switzers to warre vppon his iacke. Inuaded likewiſe from his owne niece <hi>Catherine</hi> (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretext that hir husband was adherente to the <hi>French</hi> King) the kingdome of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre</hi> her owne proper inheritance; which when he had conqueſted, hee could find no better deuiſe to aſſure it vnto himſelfe then by a falſe pretence proteſting howe he was ready to make reſtitution thereof to his neece: conditionally that leſt he ſhould be too much ouer ſeen, a truce ſhould be acor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded him for a yeere with the king of <hi>Fraunce</hi> during which in liew of reſtoring it, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified al places therof as much as he porſibly could, razed al the reſt of the citties, ſo treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:132660:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Cittadels: making expreſſe inhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that there ſhoulde not be any tillage of the earth at al, to the end he might take away all meane of recouering the places by him vſurped and fortified in the ſayd kingdome. Yet this was not all: For with his force hee could finely ſow his ſubtilty, and helpe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the cloake of religion, to make his matters the better, cauſing to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the kinge of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> husbande to his ſaid neece, for that he had taken the parte of king <hi>Lewes,</hi> the twelfth a Prince ſo good and ſo holy, that as yet of vs all hee is called by none other name, then a ſaint, and a very father of the people, and vpon this excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication he ſente very many preachers into the kingdom to turne the peoples harts from the obedience of their true kinge and Queene their lawful Princes. And what with this matter ſucceeding ſo well vnto him, and what with the death of the ſayde kinge and Queene of <hi>Nauarre</hi> which hee ſawe fell out ſoone after within eight moneths together, hee ſuffered his young nephewe <hi>Henry</hi> their ſonne to bee trayned vppe by certaine mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the opinion of <hi>Martin Luther</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:132660:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>for the ſame effecte ſent vnto him ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly himſelfe, who drawing the Pope in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hatred, for the wronge don vnto their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to excommunicate him at the inſtance of his vncle <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> who longe before had gaped for that kingdom, it was no hard matter for them to tranſporte the heart of theſe young Princes eſpecially that of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> his wiues ſiſter to the great king <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> from the hatred of the Pope to the hatred of his very religion it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>This is then the iuſt and true meane by which the Crowne of Caſtile hath receaued her ample encreaſe, by annexing to it ſo goodly a kingdom as is that of Nauar. But what fell out afterwardes? <hi>Ferdinando</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed it a ſmall time, no more then he did the reſt of al his other Kingdomes, God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them to paſſe vnto another famely, &amp; that his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both male &amp; femile, who were many in number ſhuld die before him, except onely <hi>Joan</hi> who was maried to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> Arch-duke of Auſtria, a generous Prince, but of a very ſhort life; after whoſe deceaſe ſhe fell beſide her ſelfe, leauing notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding behinde her the two greate Princes
<pb facs="tcp:132660:5"/>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> &amp; <hi>Ferdinando</hi> ſons begotten by the Arch-duke of her owne body.</p>
                  <p>This Prince <hi>Charles</hi> beeing come to the Crowne by the death of the ſaid <hi>Ferdinando</hi> (for he ruled King, notwithſtanding his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Joan</hi> was aliue detained as priſoner by him) ſoughte by all meanes posſible the alliaunce of <hi>Fraunce</hi> promiſed by infinite Treaties (eſpecially in that of <hi>Noyon</hi>) to be accomptable for the kingdom of Nauarre, which for all tha the neuer was. And taſting more and more the ſweetnes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding, he got vnto him, &amp; made ſpeedie prouiſion for himſelfe of the two militarie Orders: of that of Saint Iames and of that of <hi>Calatraua</hi> in Spaine, to the preiudice of his brother, to whom they were reſigned: opened his eyes alſo to the Empire, obtained it, &amp; enioyed all the Kingdoms and Seigniories both left him by <hi>Ferdinando of Arragon</hi> and theſe which his mother the foole held: likewiſe the Eſtates of <hi>Flanders</hi> and the prouinces there vnto annexed, leauing his ſaid brother only ſome corner of a country towards <hi>Auſtria,</hi> wherewith after ſome wrangling betweene them he did as a moderate prince content
<pb facs="tcp:132660:6"/>himſelfe being neuer afterwards much moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued againſt his brother new created Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, but becauſe he was ſtill egging him to reſigne to his ſon Philip now at this preſent raigning, the eſtate of King of Romanes, whereof he was poſſeſt, to the ende Philip might to the preiudice of the ſaide <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando</hi> his vncle ſucceed in the empire.</p>
                  <p>Ambition moſt aſſuredly is a thing great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie deteſtable before God, who will haue men to content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with the lot which he giueth them in the earth, but the pretexts which are taken of the pure ſeruice of God, for an other ſubiect, are worſt of all, and crie for vengeance before his holy face.</p>
                  <p>I will not say this prince Charles the firſt, vnder collor of defending the catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in Germany went about (as ſom haue ſaid) to inuade the eſtate and libertie of the princes of Germany: but this <hi>I</hi> will aduouch that hee and Philip king of <hi>Spaine</hi> his ſonne haue employed themſelues (by confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his owne men, and none of his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſeruantes, the one of them yet liuing, as I thinke, the <hi>Seigneur de Champigny,</hi> not long ſince high Treaſurer in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Cardinal <hi>Granduel</hi>) towards the
<pb facs="tcp:132660:6"/>proteſtants of Germany, following the ſteps of the aboueſaid <hi>Ferdina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do</hi> of Arragon their predeceſſour, to cauſe the deceaſed king of Nauarre to bee inſtructed in the opinion of <hi>Luther,</hi> to the ende to make him the further fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the crown of France, from the alliance of the <hi>Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch,</hi> &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the recouery of his kingdom of Nauar. But if he who ſeduceth but a litle ſimple child be pronounced by Gods owne mouth to be of worſer ſtate then if hee were caſt into the bottome of the ſea, with a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone tyed about his neck, what ſhal his iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment be towards him, who ſeduceth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a child, but cauſeth others to ſeducea king &amp; a whol kingdome? but this not ſorting ſo good effect as they coulde wiſh, there were 50000. crownes ſent to the king of Nauarre then, beſides ſome horſes in gift to moue the war in France, the which 50000. crownes for al that wer refuſed witneſſes good ynough of this moſt wicked inclination &amp; vile affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> may be the Marqueſſat of <hi>Saluces,</hi> vpon the which hee hath cauſed 2. ſeuerall enterpriſes to be made by his ſon in law the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> (at the firſt it was recouered by the ſage conduct of <hi>Mounſeur
<pb facs="tcp:132660:7"/>de Rhets</hi> Marſhall of <hi>France</hi>) and the perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious league made for the ruine of al <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> nay rather of all the Eſtates of <hi>Europe,</hi> wee need no other teſtimony of his good nature and diſpoſiton towards euerie one of vs, the places borrowed in <hi>Germany</hi> from the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Liege</hi> and <hi>Colonia,</hi> there to foyſt in his garriſons when hee liſt, and to leuell right from thence at the empire, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of his cooſens, the children of <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> vnder ſhew of making ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire againſt the Proteſtants of <hi>Germanie,</hi> for the good of the Catholik religion forſooth his practiſes paſt, and euerie day put in vre in Italie, his agents ſent into Poland, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, England, Scotland, and other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the world ſay the ſame: and wel may we liken the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> to thoſe, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an inheritance wrongfullie, ſeek by greater wronges and outrages to driue the true heirs farther from the recouerie of their owne. But the iudgments of God are great, his counſels woonderfull, and the effectes of his iuſtice ineſtimable. He ſuffereth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtles ſaying, that we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lie puniſhed by thoſe againſt whom we haue
<pb facs="tcp:132660:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>treſpaſſed. The king of <hi>Spaines</hi> fathers, and he himſelfe haue ſought by all means to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine the kinges of Fraunce, and particularlie <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, raigning at this preſent: and by abuſing the muffler of religion to recoyle this lawful ſucceſſor from the crown of France, whom they ſee full of valour, and fed (as they say) with the bloud and marrow of the Lion, ready preſt one day to chalenge his iuſt inheritance. But God who hateth him more who abuſeth the holie name of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion than him who hauing bene ſeduced by purpoſed malice (as our king hath) hath tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from it: would that this king ſhould bee newe borne, who beeing deliuered from ſo manie ſnares laide to entrappe and ſnare him, hath receiued the Crowne of Fraunce, preſented vnto him by a puiſſant Armie, who hath ſubmitted it ſelf vnto him, with all the greateſt States and honeſteſt people of France. And when? Euen then when al the world iudged him by the malicious cariages and practiſed death of the deceaſed king <hi>Henry</hi> the third the fartheſt from the diadem thereof.</p>
                  <p>Germanie for her part ſhee openeth her
<pb facs="tcp:132660:8"/>eies to defend her selfe against this kinge of Spaine, who as an eagle ſuppoſeth to holde already in his tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts the empire of the whole world: The like doth Italie: and already this building of kingdomes patched together of ſo many vſurpations beginneth to diſſolue and ſhake in ſunder. Already the ſtates of Holand and Zeeland, knowing by the iuſte iudgement of God howe wrongfully they were forced and diſtracted from the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of laqueline of Henald their Countes and lawfull Princeſſe (who for to ſaue her owne ſelfe was conſtrained to forſake her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate) haue puld their necks out of the yoke, and made themſelues free, chooſing rather to die then to be ſubiect to a Domination ſo intollerable as is that of the proud Spaniard.</p>
                  <p>The prouinces of <hi>Zutphen</hi> and <hi>Gueldres</hi> taken away from their lawfull <hi>Seigneurs</hi> by the deede of guiftes which the laſte Duke <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Bourgundie</hi> who died before <hi>Nan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie</hi> ſought to get at the handes of Duke <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nald</hi> then his priſoner, to the preiudice of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dolf</hi> his ſonne, haue ſlipt the coller alſo of his obedience and the Country of Frizelande hath don no leſſe.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132660:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>The beſt aduiſed inhabitants of the lowe Countries of <hi>Flaunders Henald</hi> and <hi>Artois</hi> held out their armes to the king of Fraunce, (nor onely for the exceſſiue impoſitions (as of paying two ſhinllings for the grinding of a quarter of wheate, foure ſhillings for a cow which is the ſlaughter, or kept to giue milke, and other ſuch like petty taxes, for which they pay full deere in Flaunders) but for that they know that they are of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Demaines of the crown of France, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, making one of the members of the kingdome and being one of the principall ſeates of the twelue Peeres. They crye with a lowde voice that it was not in the power of king <hi>Frauncis</hi> the firſt (then priſoner) ſo to abandon and giue them away: and that in this caſe there ought to be reſtitution made ſeeing the lawe is held currant of all, that a priſoner locked vp faſt in priſon (as was then the ſaid king) hee is not bound to performe any promiſe made, but remaineth afterward in liberty of his faith.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe of Lille, Douay and <hi>Orchies,</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall citties of the low Countries, do know and confeſſe how by right they appertain to
<pb facs="tcp:132660:9"/>the kinge of <hi>Fraunce:</hi> for <hi>Phillip</hi> the Hardy hauing promiſed <hi>Charles</hi> the fifte kinge of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> (who let him haue them at his mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with the inheritrix of <hi>Flaunders</hi>) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe them vnto his right ſo ſoone as God ſhoulde haue called vnto him <hi>Lewes de Mayle</hi> Earle of <hi>Flaunders</hi> his father in lawe: and bound himſelfe by contract paſte at <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronn</hi> the twenty of September 1368. vnder obligation, of himſelfe, his heyres and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and vpon paine of the Apoſtolicall cenſures, wherunto the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſtands anſwerable vpon perill of his owne ſoule.</p>
                  <p>And as for <hi>Milan, Sicilie</hi> &amp; <hi>Naples,</hi> all the world knoweth what rights Fraunce hath in them all.</p>
                  <p>And as for the kingdom of <hi>Maiorica,</hi> the Earldomes of Sardinia and of Rouſsillon out of which are as yet owing to the Crown of France, the 300. thouſand crowns which <hi>Lewes</hi> the eleuenth disburſed, when they were engaged to him for that ſumme: <hi>Lewes</hi> of.<hi>Aniow</hi> had the gift thereof, which the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Marqueſſe of <hi>Montferrat,</hi> ſiſter and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heire to <hi>Iames</hi> the laſt king of <hi>Maiorica</hi> preſented him.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132660:9"/>
                  <p>As for <hi>Biſcay,</hi> it appertained to the Duke <hi>d'Alenzou</hi> of Fraunce by the right of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Maria de Lara,</hi> Lady of the ſaid country: but ſhee could neuer recouer her preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue from Henry ſecond of that name kinge of Caſtile, earle of <hi>Triſtemara,</hi> inueſted ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnieur thereof by the aide &amp; only armes of <hi>Charles</hi> 5. king of Fraunce, who ſent thither <hi>Bertrand de Gueſclin</hi> his Conſtable to ceaze it for <hi>Henries</hi> right, who inſtalled him therin. And by this king, albeit a baſtard, commeth all the title that king <hi>Phillip</hi> at this preſente raygning hath in Spaine: as in like manner from the ſide of Baſtardes commeth all the rights and titles which he pretendeth to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan, Naples, Sicilia,</hi> which are not as yet in too great aſſurance to him.</p>
                  <p>As for <hi>Arragon,</hi> beſide the quarrell of the donation made by <hi>Pope Martin</hi> ſucceſſor of <hi>Nicholas,</hi> to <hi>Philip</hi> the third king of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> or to <hi>Charles</hi> his ſecond ſonne to the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of <hi>Peter</hi> kinge of <hi>Arragon,</hi> husbande of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Manfroy</hi> of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and baſtarde to Fredericke the ſecond Emperour and king of <hi>Naples:</hi> &amp; the rights of <hi>Mathew</hi> of Caſtelbon, Earle of <hi>Foix</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:132660:10"/>
                     <hi>Bearne,</hi> on the behalfe of <hi>Joane</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Iohn</hi> ſon to king <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Arragon:</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alſo the deedes of guift paſte by <hi>Rene d' Aniou</hi> king of <hi>Sicilia</hi> to <hi>Lewes</hi> the eleuenth king of Fraunce; by whoſe only aide he was crowned king of <hi>Arragon</hi> in the citty of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellona:</hi> the houſe of <hi>Lorraine</hi> may pretende herin alſo ſom right, bicauſe of <hi>Yolant</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to the Duke of <hi>Bar</hi> maried to <hi>Lewes</hi> of <hi>Aniou,</hi> who was forced to compound for al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rights for one hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred ſixty thouſand <hi>Florins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as for Portugal, it is a thing as yet of very ſlender aſſurance in the houſe of Spain, as well by reaſon of the auncient emnity and an old quarrell which is betweene theſe two prouinces, as for the rights which may bee pretended therin amongſt other by the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors either hauing right from the houſe of <hi>Boloing</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try of <hi>Boulenois</hi> in <hi>Picardy</hi> is at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t anexed to the crown of Fraunce. For <hi>Alfonſo</hi> kinge of Portugall marying with <hi>Mahault</hi> or <hi>Mathilda</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>Boloing,</hi> had by her two children &amp; it fel out as ſhe was in the country of <hi>Boulenois</hi> to ſette order in the affaires of her husband the Earle, the K· of Portugal being rauiſhed
<pb facs="tcp:132660:10"/>with the beauty of <hi>Beatrix;</hi> baſtard daughter to <hi>Alfonſo</hi> surnamed the <hi>ſage,</hi> or <hi>Aſtrologian,</hi> King of Caſtile, Leon and Toledo, where al things were ſo well agreed vppon betweene them two, that this Caſtilian king without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ceremonie maried her, leauing <hi>Mathil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> who liued twelue yeares, during this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt mariage or rather concubinage: and being returned into Portugall, was forced to returne into Fraunce to make her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaintes to the king, and afterwards to Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth, who ſoone excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated the Portugal king and his new mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried wife. Neuertheleſſe the children of this his illigetimat wife did not forbear to vſurp the kingdom fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe who wer lawfullie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten on his firſt, <hi>Raynucio</hi> the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Parma</hi> at this preſent hath alſo moſt apparant right on the part of <hi>Maria</hi> his mother daughter to <hi>Edward,</hi> ſon to king <hi>Emanuel</hi> of <hi>Portugal:</hi> the king of <hi>Spain</hi> who hath vſurped it being iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but of one of <hi>Emanuels</hi> daughters, &amp; <hi>Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nucio</hi> being deſcended of the ſon: there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth alſo a third chalenger, <hi>Don Antonio K.</hi> of <hi>Portugal,</hi> who is the ſon prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded baſtard of Lewes the elder brother of <hi>Edward:</hi> but le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gitimated by the Pope &amp; by ſentence of the
<pb facs="tcp:132660:11"/>of the holy Sea, who after the full ſcanning of his title was elected king of portugall by the people, according to the mentall law of that kingdome.</p>
                  <p>The kinge of Fraunce <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth demandeth the kingdome of Nauarre as to him appertaining by the right of his mother, heire to that <hi>Catherine</hi> aboue ſaid, the neece of Ferdinando of Arragon: whoſe proper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance which was that kingdome, cannot be thus loſt to her dommage, when her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſhould haue fallen into ſom enormous faulte. To him appertayne the places of <hi>Soſierra</hi> depending from al antiquity of that kingdome which Queene Iſabell the firſte wife of Ferdinando by her teſtament, and for diſcharge of her conſcience gaue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that they ſhoulde bee reſtored, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bene vſurped by thoſe of Caſtile from Nauerre. To him appertains moreouer the Duchies of Gandia Mount-blanc in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon, and Pegnafiel: the Earledome of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bargorcea, the Infantaſgo of Caſtile, the cittie of Balaguer, and the Townes of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrocheris, Harao, Villalon, Cuellar, the which king <hi>John</hi> father to <hi>Ferdinando</hi> of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon
<pb facs="tcp:132660:11"/>gaue to the kingdome of Nauarre: vpon condition that in recompence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; he might enioy the ſaid kingdom during his life, whether hee had iſſue or not by his marriage with Blanch daughter to Charles king of Nauarre third of that name, beeing the little ſonne of Philip <hi>d'Eureux</hi> of the houſe of France: and there are alſo due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Maieſtie foure hundred twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande one hundred and twelue Florins of gold, ſix ſhillings eight deniers; money of Aragon, as wel can witneſſe the mariage of the ſaid Blanch to the reſtitution of all which territories and to the paiment of euerie pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of theſe ſums the king of Spaine ſtandes bounden yet at this day.</p>
                  <p>This is not al, the verie kingdome of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile may lawfullie be called in queſtion for the king of France, as being the true ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of Saint Lewes: and herein can bee no preſcription alledged. For it is neuer admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in matters concerning kingdomes, and things purchaſed by fraudulent dealing. His Maieſties right is this, Henrie the firſt of the name king of Caſtile and Toledo, ſonne to Alphonſo the 4. of Caſtile, and to <hi>Leonora,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:132660:12"/>daughter to Henrie the ſecond, king of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and to that <hi>Leonora,</hi> whome Lewes the young king of France put away, and dying without iſſue by the fall of a tileſtone vpon his heade, left his ſiſters: the elder called <hi>Blanch,</hi> mother of <hi>S.</hi> Lewes: the ſecond, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renguere,</hi> wife of the king <hi>Don Alfonſo</hi> of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and the third, <hi>Leonora</hi> wife to the king of ragon.</p>
                  <p>Nowe when the ſaide <hi>Berenguere</hi> by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinanuce of Pope <hi>Jnnocent</hi> the thirde of that name, had bene ſeperated from the King of <hi>Leon</hi> her husbande, for that they were neere in Conſanguinitie together: ſhee retyred her ſelfe after that tovvardes <hi>Henrie</hi> her brother, with her ſonne <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando,</hi> which ſhee had by the King of <hi>Leon,</hi> and hauing gotten infinite fauourites in the court of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> ſeeing the King Saint Lewes farre diſtant from her, and much buſied in other warres, ſhee handled her matters ſo cunningly to the preiudice of this S. Lewes, ſhe cauſed her ſon <hi>Ferdinando</hi> to bee elected King of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Toledo,</hi> vppon the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hope which ſhe gaue the Caſtilians, that in the perſon of her ſon ſhould the kingdom
<pb facs="tcp:132660:12"/>of <hi>Leon</hi> be reunited to that of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> &amp; that they ſhuld auoid by this mean the dominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a French Prince being but a ſtranger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. S. Lewers began quickly to look &amp; to make inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for his Kingdoms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: but whilſt they did finely hold him play with fair promiſes, to reſtore him al again: he being not able to tranſport himſelfe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reaſon of his warres in hande, the vvhole remained amongeſt them euer ſince.</p>
                  <p>I knowe well the Spaniardes alleage, that S. Lewes compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded afterwards by means of the mariage of his daughter <hi>Blanch</hi> with <hi>Ferdinando</hi> of Leon, ſon to <hi>Alfonſo</hi> the wiſe Aſtrologian, elected in fauour of the French to be Emperour of Germany, againſt <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> ſon to King <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> But grant we that it were ſo, which notwithſtanding, can neuer be accorded them, the K. of <hi>France</hi> remaineth not without a ſecond right to the ſaid Kingdoms. For afterwardes God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting not, that anie ſo vniuſt vſurpation ſhould take place, <hi>Alfonſo</hi> the ſage was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and depriued of the Empire by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulfe, elected and placed in his roome,
<pb facs="tcp:132660:13"/>in his owne life time: was alſo bereaued by Sancio his ſecond ſonne of part of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes thorough the aide of a Moore-king, named Mahomet Myr of Granado, with whom this <hi>Sancio</hi> made league to war vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his father: whereupon Alfonſo growing into great indignation, and fearing leaſt he ſhould diſpoſſeſſe the little infantes iſſued of his ſecond ſonne Ferdinando <hi>de la Cerda,</hi> but then latelie dead, to whome the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes did of right appertaine: he gaue him his curſe and diſinherited him, declaring by his Teſtament for heire in his kingdomes the eldeſt borne ſonne of his elder ſon, and in caſe he might not poſſeſſe them did ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute to the preiudice of his two other ſons Iohn and Iames, Philip ſon to S. Lewes, vnto whom (pricked with the teſtimonie of his owne conſcience) hee confeſſed theſe kingdoms of Caſtile and Toledo to apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. And in caſe the rights of Saint Lewes ſhould come to ceaſe and faile, that then theſe realmes ſhould come to the children of the ſaid Ferdinando <hi>de la Cerda,</hi> whereof there is as yet ſome remainder in Spaine, which poſsible will not be content to bee
<pb facs="tcp:132660:13"/>tongue tyed for euer. And one of the deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of this <hi>Ferdinando de la Cerde, Alfonſus</hi> who was father to <hi>John d'Eſpagne</hi> Conſtable of Fraunce, behauing himſelfe as a kinge of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Toledo</hi> made a preſent to <hi>Philip d'Eureux</hi> king of Nauarre of the country of <hi>Guipuſcoa, Alaua,</hi> and <hi>Rioia,</hi> which had ben territories and appurtenaunces of Nauarre: all which the kinge of Fraunce who is at this preſent, may as yet as kinge of Nauarre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime and iuſtlie challenge for his owne right.</p>
                  <p>I will not ſtaie my ſelfe at infinite other rights, which not onely Fraunce but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and other particular Princes may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in the dominion &amp; countries which the king of Spain holdeth (who by alluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the houſe of <hi>Auſtrich</hi> may be called <hi>Riche</hi> of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens goods.) I will not touch the ſhare which the king of Spains daughters may pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tend with his ſonne, as well in the kingdome of <hi>Leon,</hi> as in other goods partable from all times betweene ſons and daughters. Little will I alſo ſpeake of the ſignall dommage of the diuiſion of lands and goods pretended by the defuncte Emperour <hi>Ferdinando</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:132660:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Avſtria,</hi> againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt his brother, father to this king of Spaine <hi>Phillip</hi> rayning at this preſent.</p>
                  <p>What ſhould I counte the reuoults which are daily practiſed in the indies by reaſon of the intollerable impoſts, which the king of Spaine maketh them endure, who conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them to pay euery yeare (as in Spaine likewiſe) their part for the obtaining of the Popes Bull, that they may eate fleſh, egges, and cheeſe vpon fiſh dayes, both the men and women, poore and rich, of citties and villages, all without difference from ſeuen yeares of age vpwardes. And vrgeth them to this inconſideration of the expences he is at in obtaining the ſaide Bull, which none may refuſe to take, albeit he woulde neuer eate butter and cheeſe in all his life. And that which is taken for a head in Spaine, is two Reals which is twelue pence ſterling, and in the Indies is taken for euery poule eighteene or tweenty Reales: Counte you after the rate what it doth amounte vnto in ſuch a world of people: and without the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide Bull, none may nor ought not (as ſaye theſe good hirelings preachers of Perdons)
<pb facs="tcp:132660:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>be buried in hallowed grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, nor once come within the Church doore. O abhominable abuſe! O ſinne againſte the holy-ghoſt! of thoſe who terming themſelues defendours of religion, ſell vnto their owne ſubiects, the help &amp; ſuccour which they ſay to obtain for the health of their ſoules! See what a goodly reuenewe this is, and like to bee be long time fauored of God. But in the meane time it is the greateſt of all Spaine. O miſerable and vnnaturall French men, who cloſing your eies to ſo many iniquities, do ſuffer your ſelues to bee ſeduced by this GOLDE ſo ill gotten.</p>
                  <p>There remaineth their inquiſition which ſerueth their turne rather to rob the goods of the innocent and miſerable, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine men in any religion, wherof they were but as it were a maske an muffler.</p>
                  <p>Thus Spaine groweth to bee diſpeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled by theſe cruelties intollerable and by the <hi>Alcaualle,</hi> which they call the tenthpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of euery thing boughte and ſoulde, yea of the very habit which you ſhall cary newe in your cloake bagges. Who ſhall then
<pb facs="tcp:132660:15"/>bee the man ſo miſerable that will admit in our Fraunce ſuch people, whoſe very name is ſo ill receaued and odious, that to name them only skarreth the little children, and maketh them affrayde? Alas: Take heede, Frenchmen, it be not reproched you before God, how ye haue chaced away your owne brethren to lodge among you, barbarous people, take heede that this curſe fall not vpon your heads, to be called iuſtlie Vipers who teares out the entrals of your own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is to ſay, of your own natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: &amp; beleeue that euerie one that wold ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine the building of Fraunce, ſhall remaine buried in the ruines. But if the lawes do pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh a man for hauing ſlaine a man who is his like, by how much more ſtrong reaſon ſhall thoſe be puniſhed, who do not only kill a man, but procure the entire death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of a kingdome?</p>
                  <p>The king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who here to fore ſaid, that we muſt come to no tretie of peace with our king being ſwarued from the faith, cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not in the mean time, and giueth not yet ouer to aſſay by all meanes to make peace with his ſubiects of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> who
<pb facs="tcp:132660:15"/>are Lutheriens, Caluiniſts or Anabaptiſtes. He offreth to leaue them their free exerciſe of religion, to let them haue their citties and gouernments in the ſame eſtate wherin they poſſeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, demandeth only at their handes that they woulde but acknowledge him for their king. But thoſe States ful wel knowe to whom they appertaine, and what manner a thing the Spaniſh domination is, &amp; that this nation doth applaud, as doth the Crocodile when ſhe wil caſt forth her venome or bite: witnes be the poor Earls of <hi>Aignemont</hi> &amp; of <hi>Horn</hi> put cruelly to death, notwithſtanding their ſeruices done, for the reducing of coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tries into his obedience, &amp; the faith to them promiſed. The death alſo procured by poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as is ſaid to the poor Lord of <hi>Montigny</hi> the end of the poore Marqueſſe of <hi>Bergues,</hi> and of al the Nobility which by one or other meane they race and root cleane out.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth can wel tel how to defie all their falſe drifts, &amp; he miſtruſteth their cunning cariages, for all their ſending him the portraite of the infant: He may too well knowe, how when <hi>Ferdinando</hi> of Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon the laſt, &amp; <hi>Philip</hi> Archduk of Auſtria,
<pb facs="tcp:132660:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>were in treaty of the mariage of <hi>Madam Claudi</hi> of Fraunce with <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, the father of this <hi>Philip</hi> nowe rayning, and after the mariage concluded, ſworne and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at <hi>Blois,</hi> the king of Fraunce <hi>Lewes</hi> the twelfth his Lieutenants miſtruſting nothing the Spainards ranne vppon them defeating two French Armies the one in <hi>Calabria</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Conduct of the Lord <hi>d'Anbig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> the other at <hi>Cirignolla</hi> lead by the Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> the Lord <hi>Lewes d'Armignac:</hi> the chiefe commanders of the Spaniards alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for all excuſes that they had heard of no prohibition giuen them from their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to make warres.</p>
                  <p>At this preſent the king of Spaine being of the age of ſixty 7. yeares and aboue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtly of his perſon (as he is doubtles) ſeeth himſelfe at the period of his ſubtilties, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tel by what meanes to keepe that which he hath purloined from others; his faire pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſes vapour away to nothing, his mind is bewrayed and his counſels diſcouered. Hee ſeeketh to helpe himſelfe with the feebler ſide in Fraunce, to the end to keepe vs ſtil in war, for feare leaſt the weaker parte through
<pb facs="tcp:132660:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>want of means ſhould abando<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n the war, hee would make vs knocke one another on the heades, that he may make his preie on vs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward. He goeth about to cut our throats with our own kniues, and to ouerthrowe vs with our owne weapons, becauſe by his hee knoweth he cannot do it. He entertaineth the warre in our country, for feare leaſt wee ſet vpon him in his owne: And if that parte which he taketh ſhould become the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he would incontinent war vpon it. He is not yet come to ſollicite (as they call them) the <hi>Huguenotes</hi> of <hi>Fraunce</hi> to rebell againſt King <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, and to wage warre vpon him.</p>
                  <p>Let then all Princes and Potentates take heed of the enterpriſes and counſels of ſo charitable a neighbour: And you French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, learn to be wiſe by your owne harmes: I adiure you all by the honour and reſpect you beare vnto God, by the faith, loue and loyaltie you owe to King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, giuen by God vnto Fraunce, ſonne to your predeceſſor Kings, iſſued from the loynes of S. <hi>Lewes,</hi> and by the charity yee owe to your countrie, and to the ſafetie of your ſelues, of
<pb facs="tcp:132660:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>your wiues and of your children, and to the conſeruation of our religion, Temples and Fortunes, ceaſe among your ſelues this pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh rebellion (if as yet it haue place in anie of you) and reduce it to a due obedience, which onely can make next after the grace of God ſpring againe vpon vs the bliſſe of our fathers and the peace and tranquillitie of their golden ages.</p>
                  <p>Some preach that religion is in great ieopar die, &amp; that many of the fathers in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church are dead for the catholick faith, and that we muſt die for the ſame: I grant it, but they muſt giue vs the Scriptures as they are vnderſtood. We are already to die when they ſhal force vs to renounce our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; to ſacrifice vnto Idols. Then and no otherwiſe ought death to bee endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this caſe, ſo haue thoſe fathers recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, &amp; we will die before we will bee other than followers of the true Catholike and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike religion. Our fathers in the church fled in time of perſecution &amp; none of them haue reſiſted kings in armes, finding it better to ſuffer then to reuolt. Our Lord alſo coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled his Apoſtles to flie in time of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:132660:17"/>from one cittye to an other, and not to make any reſiſtance by armes.</p>
                  <p>And ye the Lords of the Cleargy, knowe ye that the doctrine which God hath giuen vs (to you principally as a pledge of his grace) hall neuer gette his perfect and reſplendent brightneſſe, as long as theſe bloudy warres ſhall trouble the ſweete ſtreams flowing from ſo goodly a fountain. O how the league doth well ſhew it ſelfe to be come from the loweſt cauernes of hell, ſith it putteth diuiſion name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among the Catholikes, who being vnited together might liuely haue ſet vpon the Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes and by faire war cut off many thouſands of them. Knowe that you haue neede of the materiall ſword, which is that of the kinge, to make you liue in ſafety, reſt, and iuſtice, and to maintain this our religion which is the trew ſoule of the body of our eſtate. And ſure, needefull it is to conſerue the kingdome in his entire body without diuiding it into his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, for fear leaſt by the cutting off of ſom one principall, this ſoule take his flight away. Behold I pray you the fruit of the preachings of ſome amongſt you, and poſſible (albeit not all) moued with a good zeale but not ruled
<pb facs="tcp:132660:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>as ſaith the Apoſtle according to knowledge but what haue you done? trulie you haue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed bellows and ſtraw to kindle the coales of our quarrel. O furie: O madneſſe: vnbeſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming your Prieſthood. So is it come to paſſe, that millions of your flocks are periſhed with out confeſsion, without ſacramentes, without ſepulture: Of a hundred Churches ſcarce ſhal ye finde one ſtanding whole, nor in ten pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes hardlie one pariſh-prieſt, if it bee not in the countries reduced to the Kinges obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. This was the matter that moued <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Vigor,</hi> one of the moſt famous Doctors of diuinitie in <hi>France,</hi> &amp; for his ſingular lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning made by the holie Father Archbiſhop of <hi>Narbona</hi> to ſay in his ſermons vppon the feaſt of Trinitie and S. <hi>Martin: Jf God woulde ſo much afflict vs as to giue vs a King who were a Turke or an Heretike, yet muſt not wee leuie Armes againſte him, nor warre vppon him, for the great miſchiefes which enſue thereupon.</hi> Theſe very words are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in the books imprinted before the troubles, but are mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſlie put out in the new imprinted by the League, for feare leaſt this knife of truth ſhuld cut the throate of theſe ſuppoſtes of 1eaſing,
<pb facs="tcp:132660:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>who could not abide ſo good a leſſon in ſo good an authour.</p>
                  <p>But now our King is, God bee thanked, moſt Catholike, and when hee were not ſo, God who cauſed himſelf to be enregiſtred in the records of the Emperour <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> when he cauſed the whole world to be taxed: &amp; the commandement to pay the tribute vnto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> albeit he were a prophane Pagan: the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample alſo of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> who appealed vnto <hi>Nero</hi> a moſt wicked Emperour, ſhew that the King being ſuch as God ſendeth to take the royal place, is to be obeyed. The examples likewiſe of the thirtie three Popes being all martyrs, &amp; died conſecutiuelie one after ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther haue ſhewed vs the ſame, who neuer cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſword to be vnſheathed againſt the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting emperours or any other heretikes.</p>
                  <p>The ſame did <hi>S. Gregory</hi> the Pope, dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his dialogues to <hi>Theodolinda</hi> wife to <hi>Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lulphus</hi> King of <hi>Lombards,</hi> holding as yet then his paganiſme that thorow the ſweet perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his vvife, he might be brought to chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſme &amp; purchaſe peace vnto the church. Did not Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the like proſtrating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at the feet of the vvicked <hi>Attilas.</hi> No leſſe did Pope Iohn the firſt of that name,
<pb facs="tcp:132660:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>going from Rome to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to the Emperour <hi>Iuſtin,</hi> to pray him to ſet open the Temples of the Arrians, which he had cauſed to be ſhut vp fearing leaſt the Arrians, which might conſume of themſelues, would diſturb and trouble the peaceable eſtate &amp; tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Church.</p>
                  <p>Doubt ye not alſo but that our holy father the Pope moued by theſe examples wil ſeeke to repaire the wrong donne vnto our king, by ſome miſinformed of his iuſtice, or posſibly caried headlong away with the Spaniſh paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. He ſhall find him to bee ſuch a one that he is the eldeſt ſonne of the Church: hee will call to mind how our king is deſcended from thoſe, who haue conſecrated and giuen in almes to the Church, the faireſt flowers of their garland, and the beſt of their good. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! His holineſſe cannot do leſſe for our king <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, then by one of his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors hath beene donne within theſe fewe yeares to the Quene of <hi>Sweden</hi> being excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated and in relapſe, receauing her with all ioy and gladneſſe in the perſon of her em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors into the boſome of the church.</p>
                  <p>The holie fathers haue neuer refuſed the
<pb facs="tcp:132660:19"/>penitent princes, witneſſe bee the peace of Conſtance and other decrees, wherof the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories and holie Councels are fully repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. His Holineſſe may ſee how much is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied the ſhare, which god hath giuen our king in the earth: But hee ſhall ſay to the king of <hi>Spain,</hi> the greateſt ſpiter thereof, that which Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8 told moſt wiſely <hi>Albertus</hi> of Auſtria, who by his cunning working cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe to be elected Emperour, to the preiudice of <hi>William</hi> Earle of Naſſau, then Emperour of Germanie, whome he ſlewe in battel, he ſhal tel him, I ſay, that hee who hath ſlaine the Emperour with his own hand is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to bee inueſted and confirmed in the Empire. For it is by his onely hand and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that this death and ſlaughter is purchaſed in our kingdom of France, wherein he went about and was willing to cauſe himſelfe to be called king, but God bee thanked, hee hath loſt his labour therein.</p>
                  <p>The holie father who was in the time of <hi>Ema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuel</hi> Emperor of the Eaſt, wold not once har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the offers hee made him to cauſe the Greek Church to bee reunited with the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine vpon condition that the Empire of the
<pb facs="tcp:132660:20"/>Weſt, being vacant by reaſon of the depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Frederick,</hi> ſhuld be reunited with that of the Eaſt: foreſeeing alſo that it was a matter greatly to be ſuſpected whereby to make the vniuerſall Church, to depende but of one only power among men: and ſhould his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe ſo much weaken a King or a kingdom, of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which is the true arme of the church to ſuffer all the world to be ouerflowne with a king and a prouince meer mixed with races of Moores, Saracens and Gothes, than with true Chriſtians, hauing more holines and reſpect to ſacred thinges, than is borne to the leaſt village in Fraunce?</p>
                  <p>His Holineſſe ſhall know that the kinges of Fraunce &amp; their peoples haue bent their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; made good for the Church, then when Aſia, Afrike, Spaine, Italie, and almoſt all the world were full of Arrianiſme and hereſies, let him remember alſo (and his ſucceſſors may for euer cal happilie to remembrance in their holy ſea) how that in the year of the birth of king <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> at this preſent was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and diſmall to the holie Sea, hauing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Army of Charles the fifth his father, ſurpriſed and ſackt Rome, ranſommed the
<pb facs="tcp:132660:20"/>holy father <hi>Clement</hi> and his cardinals ruined &amp; profaned the temples &amp; churches of Rome which <hi>Attilas</hi> beeing named for his inhumain cruelties, the ſcourge of God, refuſed, to do.</p>
                  <p>King Henry the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> knoweth right wel, that he muſt one day giue accompt of his charge, &amp; that God wil cauſe him to be obeyed, honored and ſerued of his ſubiects, as he wil obey, honour and ſerue God: Hee knoweth how the firſt marſhall, king and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the whole worlde <hi>Adam,</hi> before his fall, was reſpected of all liuing creatures, as Lord thereof, but after his reuolte the verie beaſtes rebelled againſt him, the Lyon began to diſmember &amp; tear him in peeces, the horſe to kick and winch at him, the dog to ſnarl and bite at him, and ſo al the reſt in their kinds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to bende all the vigour of their furies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him and that God hath poſſibly permit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the ſame to be done to him by ſome of his ſubiects (albeit if they turn not again to their allegeance, they can neuer eſcape the diuine vengeance, becauſe their king hath by the ſuggeſtion of his enemies wandered aſtray in Religion. His Maieſty knoweth too well that hee cannot purchaſe the grace of God if being aduanced by him into a more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb facs="tcp:132660:21"/>than they in all maner of vertuous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Hee ſheweth already by the diligence which he vſeth in feats of armes, that as he is far gone in the iourny of his age; and ther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining for him ſo many things to be done in the world (the honour and labour whereof it ſeemeth that God hath reſerued for him) he wil imitate the birds of the more northen na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, where the day hauing but one hower of length, they flie more couragiouſly &amp; more ſwiftly then any other of the aire. For he hath in a ſmall time reduced into his obedience the moſt of the people of his kingdome, and ſheweth them by the mild dealing he vſeth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, that he hath conquered them not for his owne particular good, but to bring them into their greater eaſe and ſecuritie.</p>
                  <p>Alreadie his Maieſty doeth meditate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but to make of his court the cabinet of the moſt excellent &amp; rareſt thinges of the earth, and that therein ſhall be found the moſt vertuous, honeſt, and beſt accompliſhed men of this world. Vertue ſhall be in eſteem if euer it were: he pretendeth ſo ſoon as he ſhal haue ſatiſfied thoſe vnto whom his people (miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as it is) hath for their follies paſt conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:132660:21"/>to promiſe recompences, quite to aboliſh, or ſo to moderate the taxes that his poore ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes ſhal haue cauſe for euer to pray vnto the Almightie for him, and his memorie therefore may be ſacred to all poſteritie. He is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant how by the too great exceſſe of the ſaide taxes his people remaineth in languiſhing ſort, &amp; the nobilitie who followeth him is made poor becauſe the Pezant cannot nor dare not till the lands of the nobility &amp; of others for fear of the ſaid taxes, by means wherof the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhould ly barren, without tillage, &amp; the Nobilitie, which hath no other riches but of the glebe &amp; ſoyl can no longer follow and ſerue him, nor the people of the country, or husbandman the verie forge of all commodities of the kingdome, ſuccour him any longer.</p>
                  <p>Yee then of the Nobility (if there bee any of this qualitie who wil againſt the deuoir of his profeſsion weare the skarfe of the League in ſteed of our white collour of the flowres de Luce of France) what honor think you to leaue to your children, to ſay that you haue foſtered and nouriſhed this moſtrous <hi>Hydra</hi> the league, which hath brought foorth vnto vs &amp; our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſo many miſchiefs and miſeries. See you that you ſtop vp the light and brightnes of your
<pb facs="tcp:132660:22"/>races vnder the ſinders of your rebellion? Take ye, take ye the collour of your brethren, and permit not that your noble race remaine vila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, ſtayned and ſpotted with treaſon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wads your ſelues, and towardes you countrie.</p>
                  <p>And you good people whoſe proſperity is ſo much different from that in which our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed kings and fathers left you, behould the ſurface of our poore country aunciently ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with your goodly buildings (I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſpeak this without teares) nowe deſert, rugged and without tillage. Where is this liberty promiſed you by the league? Alas! (As ſaid, <hi>I</hi> thinke <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophraſtus'</hi> to the Greekes.) <hi>(They haue put in too much vinegre,)</hi> where is this abolition of taxes? Alas; they are ſix fold as many as they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Where is this reſtabliſhment of religion? Alas they haue beaten downe to the grounde and profaned your churches; the prieſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues taking armes haue run into a thouſande villainies. Conſider that there is in Fraunce neither iuſtice nor publik force, but from your king, which may ſauegard ye from iniury. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ye not how you empoueriſh your ſelues daly, and that theſe hunger-ſtarued gouernors whoſe rebellion ye nouriſh, will ſtifle you one of theſe daies to haue your bloud, will flea you
<pb facs="tcp:132660:22"/>to haue your skins, ſeeing that amongſt them the richeſt hath nought to liue vpon, if it be not vpon your ſubſtance, nor any commoditie, which they forge not alreadie vpon your bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Anuile. Liue, liue vnder your king, and vnder his lawes, chace far from you theſe hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-preachers of ſedition, this miſerable fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and deſtroyers of our countrie: it is not religion but rebellion they preach: away with them. The Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> acknowledgeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie that he hath bene deceiued and abuſed by them. All the world knoweth it: and there is hope, ſeeing that the Crowne (as ſaid <hi>Titus Veſpatians</hi> ſon, called for his vertue and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the delight and darling of the worlde) is a gift of God, beſtowed on him whome hee pleaſeth by his onlie hand and pure will, that the ſaid Duke of <hi>Maine</hi> will reknowledge his Maieſtie for his King, and will repoſe more confidence in him than in any other prince li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. Well hee knoweth that the <hi>Maximees</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> are firſt to make a hande of them, who aide them in the Conqueſt of their prouinces, ſaying iuſtlie that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not credit the faith of them who haue failed in that which they owe to their owne countrie: and when all that were not ſo, neuer was there man who followed them
<pb facs="tcp:132660:23"/>but is dead miſerably. The ſaid Duke of <hi>Maine,</hi> hath done but too much for his part, when hee had had place but to reuenge the death of his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherunto K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. was neuer con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenting. If he paſſe further, he remaneth for euer moſt culpable and blameworthy. Let him not then let ſlip this good occaſion, whileſt the time is that he may come in and yeeld himſelf to his king with honor, making ſhew of the common pretext of religion, &amp; of no other thing to haue mooued him to take armes, and let him call to minde how hee hath to deale with a kinge of France who ſhal neuer be without ſucceſſor to reuenge all iniuries: that his maieſty may one day come to an accord with the K. of Spaine, and ſo then by that meane this Duke may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine oppreſſed and of ſmall eſteeme. Let him confeſſe that euery Chriſtian ought to leuell onely at the ſaluation of his ſoule, the which he can neuer obtain at Gods hands, nor any good for his children, but in reſtoring vnto his kinge that which he detained vniuſtly from his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, againſt the dutie of a ſubtect, a vaſſall and an officer to the crowne.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="record">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132660:23"/>
                  <head>A COPIE OF SPECI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ALL RECORD, OF THE Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage done by Philip Archduke of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, Earle of Flanders, &amp;c. to the most Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King of France, Lewes the twelft of that name, in the yeare</hi> 1499.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>ohn Amys,</hi> Notary, and Secretary to the King our Soueraigne. For ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it hath pleaſed the Noble and puiſſant L. <hi>Monſieur Guy</hi> of <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> Knight, Lord of <hi>Pleuuot,</hi> and of <hi>Laber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemant,</hi> Chauncellour of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> as well of his fauour to preferre mee, as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund and inioyne me to take a copy of the receipte of an Homage done to the King our gracious Lorde, in his perſon, by the moſt high &amp; moſt puiſſant Prince,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132660:24"/>the Lord <hi>Philip,</hi> ſonne to the King of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> Arch-duke of <hi>Austria,</hi> Earle of <hi>Flanders,</hi> of <hi>Artois,</hi> and of <hi>Charrolois,</hi> the fift at day of Iuly, 1499. the ſaide Lorde Chancellour being then in the Cittie of <hi>Arras,</hi> in the Biſhoppes pallace: And for that ſuch great actes, and ceremonies, which haue bin vſed and obſerued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to the honour, exaltation, profit, and aduantage of the King and his Crowne, are worthie of perpetuall memorie: I haue beene ſo bolde at his inſtance, to couch in writing, all that I could ſee and vnderſtand, touching this preſent act and buſines, and eſpecially ſince the nine and twentie of Iune laſt paſt, vntill the fift of Iuly, next enſuing. And to come to the matter, certaine and true it is, that the Lord Chancellor departed the ſame day, at after dinner, from <hi>Dourlent</hi> in the countrie of <hi>Picardy,</hi> to goe for the Cittie of <hi>Arras,</hi> where he arriued before night, being all the way accompanied with the Lordes <hi>de Rauestain,</hi> and <hi>de la Gruture,</hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:132660:24"/>with <hi>Charles de la <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ernada,</hi> Knight of the ſame place, Maſter <hi>Christopher de Cremona,</hi> Counſellers of ſtate and ordinarie Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Requeſts of the Kings houſe, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Ralfe de Launoy</hi> Baily of <hi>Amiens,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Francis d'Estain, Hugh de Baigel, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maury de Quinqui ville, Nicholas de Foix, Philip d'Estas, Richard Nepueu, Peter de la <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ernada,</hi> common Counſellers: <hi>Macé Toustain,</hi> the Kings Proctor generall in his Priuie Counſell, <hi>John Bourdelot,</hi> the Kings Proctor generall in his Courte of Parliament at <hi>Paris: Antony le <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iste,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of the Chauncery of <hi>France: Dreux Budé, John de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illebreſme, Ralfe Guyot, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Maillart,</hi> Notaries and Secretaries to his Maieſtie and to me. And as the Lord Chauncellor came with this traine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a mile and halfe of the Cittie of <hi>Arras,</hi> riding in gallant order, hauing before him the Gentleman Vſher of the priuie Councell, carrying vpon his ſhoulder in open ſight his mace, grauen and imboſſed with the Kings Armes: after the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132660:25"/>Vſher followed next the Clarke of the Signet, who carried the Scale, as the vſe is, when the Lord Chauncellor rideth his circuits into the Countrey: on either ſide of this Clarke of the Signet, marched one of the two kinges of Armes of our Lord the King, enrobed with their coates of Armes, to wit, <hi>Mont-ioye,</hi> the chiefe king of Armes of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Normandie:</hi> here came to meete the Lorde Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, the Biſhop of <hi>Cambray, Thomas de Pleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> Knight, Chancellor to the Archduke, the Lorde Earle of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> the Lorde of <hi>Fiennes,</hi> and diuers others both Knightes and Squiers, moſt of them of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dukes Councell. The Biſhop addreſſing himſelfe towards the Chancellor, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto him; that the Lordes of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie were ſent by the Archduke his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to informe him, that the ſaide Lorde Archduke was moſt ioyfull of his ariuall, and likewiſe of that, of all the other Lords in traine with him, &amp; that they were al the welco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt men that might be, with other
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132660:25"/>faire ſpeeches, gentle greetings, &amp; ſweete ſalutations: all this nobilitie doing great reuerence and honour to the L. Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and giuing princely entertainement to all the Nobles of his troupe: for the which the L. Chancellor returned moſt honorable thankes to the Archduke, and to the other Lordes, who were come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his behalfe. And ſoone after they on both ſides tooke their way to goe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cittie. As the whole company arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the entrance of the Suburbes, the Chancellor was met by the Archduke himſelfe, who to receiue him the more honorablie, and to meete him by the way, was departed on horſebacke from the Abbey of Saint <hi>Vas,</hi> in the Cittie of <hi>Arras,</hi> and had paſſed cleane through the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſtreete thereof. And ſo ſoone as the Archduke, accompanied with a great number both of Knightes of his order, with Squiers and other officers of his houſehold, who were marſhalled on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide, to make way and place for the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132660:26"/>Chancellor, and thoſe of his traine to paſſe, perceiued the Chancellor, hee put his hand to his hatte, and vncouering his head, haſtened on his Mule to march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Lorde Chancellor, whom hee embraced, holding ſtill his hat in hand, and there gaue him the gentle welcome: demaunding him in this manner, How dooth my Lorde the King? To whom the Chancellor anſwered, very well God bee thanked, as hee intended to declare vnto him more amply. The like great enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement gaue this Archduke to the Lordes of <hi>Rauestain</hi> and <hi>la Gruture,</hi> ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting graciouſly the Maſters of Requeſts, and the other of the Kings Counſaile, who were there preſent. After many friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeeches and countenances paſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Archduke, the Chancellor, and the Lorde <hi>Rauestain,</hi> the Archduke holding ſtill his hatte in his hand, and would not bee couered, except the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor would alſo put on: the Archduke and the Chancellor roade on their way,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132660:26"/>to enter into the Cittie, the Chancellor ſtill holding the right hand, and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman Vſher to the Kings Councel, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp his mace in open ſight, and the Clarke of the Signet, hauing the Kinges ſeale vpon his backe, as the cuſtome is, when the Chancellor rideth thorough the Kingdome, and the two Kinges of Armes in their order, nor was there any other there, on the behalfe of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke or Chancellor: which thing was, and hath been greatly noted, as well by the Archdukes people and officers, as by the other Cittiſens and Countrie, whereof there was no ſmall number, both within the Cittie and without, thither flocked to beholde this their magnificent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance. Thus the Archduke conducted along the Lorde Chancellor ſtill parling vnto him, vncouering his head often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and by no meanes would not put on againe, except the Chancellor were couered as ſoone as hee: and thus did hee bring him along, vnto the verie porch of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132660:27"/>the cloyſter of the great Church: whence the Archduke would by all force carrie him into the Biſhops Pallace, in the which the Lorde Chancellor hath alwaies been lodged, nor coulde the entreaties and requeſts which the Chancellor made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him to content himſelfe, that hee had done ſo much vnto him for the honour of his King preuaile any thing at all. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe enterparlies, the Archduke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from the Chancellor, withdrew himſelfe into the Cittie of <hi>Arras,</hi> to his lodging in Saint <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>as</hi> his Abbey: and the Lorde Chancellor into the Biſhops pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, accompanied with the Earle of <hi>Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> and other great perſonages of the Archdukes house: and afterward euerie one of the Chancellors trayne retyred themſelues into ſuch lodgings as the her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingers had appoynted for them. After many goings and commings to and fro, which by the Lorde Biſhoppe <hi>Thomas de Pleures,</hi> the Countie <hi>Naſſau,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Mont-labais,</hi> and other of the Archdukes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132660:27"/>officers; during all the dayes of Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, Tueſday, Wedneſday and Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following, being the firſt, ſecond, third, and fourth, of Iuly, were made to the Chauncellour into his lodging, to treate and conclude vpon ſome poynts and articles propounded by the Kinges Proctor generall in his Courte of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament. The ſaid matters comming to an iſſue, upon thurſdaye requeſt was made by the Archdukes officers to the Lorde Chancellor, that he would prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to receiue the Homage which the ſaide Archduke was bound to doe to the King, by reaſon of his Peere-dome and Earledome of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and likewiſe for his Countries of <hi>Artois</hi> and <hi>Charrolois,</hi> and other territories helde of the King our Soueraigne becauſe of his Crowne: and for this purpoſe to aſſigne a daye and hower to the Archduke, to the end hee might come to him to doe his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. To whom the Chauncellor gaue this aunſwere: that vpon the morrowe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132660:28"/>which was Friday, and the fift daye of the moneth, were it about nine or ten a clocke in the morning hee ſhoulde bee readie to take it: the which both daye and houre were accepted by thoſe the Archdukes officers. For this purpoſe the Lord Chauncellor gaue commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to prouide and ſet in order a place in the ſecond great hall of his lodging, the which ſhould bee hanged rounde about with rich Tapiſtries, and therein another little place to be moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted higher then the reſt by two ſteppes, where ſhould bee ſet a chayre of eſtate, coſtly trimmed, and couered with flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er de luces euery where embrodered in golde, on the which hee would bee ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, during the dooing of this Homage: and gaue them the wordes which were to bee pronounced touching this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, which was all done accordingly. Fryday being come, about the hower of ten a clocke in the morning, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor being in his chamber accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132660:28"/>with the Maſters of Requeſtes of the Kings houſe, thoſe of his Counſell, the Baylie of <hi>Amiens,</hi> and all the reſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue named, worde was brought him by Maſter <hi>Thomas de Pleures,</hi> and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Archdukes officers, how the Archduke was departed from his lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and was comming towards him to doe his Homage, and that hee ſhoulde diſpoſe and ſeate himſelfe in place con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, to receiue the ſame. To whome the Chauncellor replied, that ſo ſoone as hee ſhoulde appeare in the place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for the receite thereof, he was and woulde bee readie. Two ſeuerall times beſide this, came there other his officers, both of his Chamberlains and Secretaries, to tell him the firſt time how the Archduke was arriued, in the firſt hall, which ioyned to the ſecond, albeit the Chancellor moued not a whit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And at the ſecond time, for that thoſe officers affirmed their Lorde the Archduke was entered into the ſecond
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132660:29"/>hall, as true it was, and alſo for that the Lorde <hi>de la Gruture,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Robert de Framezelles</hi> the Kings Chamberlaine, who with the Lorde <hi>de Rauestain,</hi> had accompanied the Archduke from his lodging into the ſaid ſecond great hall, came to certifie the Chauncellour how the Archduke was alreadie in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place, appoynted and prouided for the ſaide Homage: then the Chancellor attyred in a robe of Crymſon Veluet, and with his hat on his head came one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foorth of his chamber, which ioyned cloſe to the great hall, in manner as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: You muſt then knowe, the Lord Chancellor had before him the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Vſher of the priuie Counſell, cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Mace aloft in open ſight, who ſo ſoone as hee was come foorth of the Chamber, and entered into the ſecond great hall, becauſe therein was alreadie ſo great a number of people thronging one on another, as wel of the Archdukes officers as of others, that a man coulde
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132660:29"/>hardly turne himſelfe, beganne with a loude voyce to crye out in theſe wordes three or foure times: Roome, Roome, make Roome my maſters, giue place there before. After the ſaide Vſher marched the two kings of Armes of our King, enrobed with our Kinges coates of Armes: then followed the Chauncel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and after him the Maſters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes of the priuie Counſell, and then the Notaries and Secretaries of the King our Lorde with whom I was. And for that the Lorde Chancellor gaue me commaund before his departure out of his chamber, that I ſhould take vp ſome place fit to beholde the ſaide Homage, and to heare as well the wordes of him, as of the Archduke, which ſhould be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and ſpoken by them both, and to ſet downe the ſame in writing, as I might beſt deuiſe, I was not negligent to doe it. And you muſt knowe as the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor approached the chayre, wherein hee was to ſitte downe, the Archduke, who
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132660:30"/>ſtoode hard by it, attending the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the ſaide Lorde Chancellor, put off his bonnet incontinent, and thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpake the Chancellor: My Lorde, GOD giue you good morrowe, and with that bowed his head very low: but the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor without ſpeaking any worde at all, put onely his hand to his hat hee had on his head, not dooing it off at all, then ſat him downe in his chayre, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with one of the kinges of Armes, as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was giuen him b the Chauncellor, cryed with a loude voyce three times: Peace, Silence, keepe Silence there. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, the Archduke bare headed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelfe to the Lorde Chancellor to doe his Homage, ſaying: My Lord, I am come to you to doe the Homage which I am bound to doe to my Lorde the King, touching my Peere-dome and Countries of <hi>Flanders, Artois,</hi> and <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolois,</hi> the which I holde of my Lorde the King, by the right of his Crowne. Then the Lorde Chauncellour ſitting in his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132660:30"/>chayre, his hat vpon his head, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him whether hee had any girdle, dagger, or other weapon: to whome the Archduke lifting vp the laps of his cote, which was vngirded, replied, hee had none. So ſoone as hee had ſo ſaide, the Chauncellor put both his two hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his owne, and holding them ſo faſt ioyned together, the Archduke would haue bowed himſelfe downe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſhew to fall on his knees, which the Chauncellor woulde not permit him to do: but in lifting him vp againe by his two hands, which hee held faſt as wee ſaide before, ſpake theſe wordes: Your good will ſuffiſeth. Then the Chauncel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor began with him in this manner, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtill his handes faſt cloſed within his, the ſaide Archduke ſtanding all this while bare headed, and forcing himſelfe to fall vpon his knees: You become the vaſſal of the King your Soueraign Lord, and you doe him faith and liege Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, by reaſon of your Peere-dome
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132660:31"/>and Earledome of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and alſo of the Earledomes of <hi>Arthois,</hi> and of <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolois,</hi> and of all other the landes which you holde, which are of his demaynes and held of the King in right of his Crowne: you promiſe to ſerue him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till death incluſiuely towardes and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte all thoſe who may liue and dye, excepting none: to procure his good, and to auoyde his hurt, and to carrie and acquire your ſelfe towards him, as towards your Soueraine Lord. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the Archduke made this anſwere: By my faith ſo I promiſe, and ſo will I performe it. This done and ſaide, the Lorde Chauncellour vſed theſe wordes vnto him: And I receiue you, excepting the right of the King in other thinges, and others in all. Afterward hee turned his cheeke to him, on the which the Lord Chauncellor kiſt him. When the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke requeſted and demanded at the Chancellors handes letters teſtimoniall of the receite of the ſaid homage, which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:132660:31"/>the Chancellor commanded me to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch and giue him. Then the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor roſe vp from his chaire, and vncoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his head, did his reuerence to the Archduke with theſe tearmes. My Lord I did euen nowe ſupply the office of a King, repreſenting his perſon, and at this preſent I am but <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Rochefort,</hi> your moſt humble ſeruant, alwayes ready to ſerue you, towardes the King my Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord and Maſter, in whatſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe you to commaund me: whereof the Archduke gaue him many harty tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks, with theſe curteous words: my Lorde Chancellor I thanke you, and beſeech you euermore that you will in all mine affaires towardes my Lorde the King, thinke vpon me and haue me in remembrance.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Witnes my manual ſeale put hereunto <date>the firſt day of Auguſt. 1499.</date>
                     </dateline> 
                     <signed>Sic Signatum. AMYS.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A true Copy taken forth of the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Recordes, regiſtred in the Court of Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> thus ſigned: <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> TJLLEL.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:132660:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132660:32"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>TO THE WORTHIE, AND FAVOROR OF ALL VERTVES, MASTER RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARD SONDS, SONNE and heire to the right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, Michael Sondes Eſquier.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir the duetie I owe vnto you, proceeding of ſo many &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit curtiſies, in all bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful meaſure receiued, as well in your forraine trauailes, as in your home aboad, haue of long time been a continuall ſpurre to my weake forces; to finde ſome defence against that threatning monster ingratitude; &amp; fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wayward fortune ſtill waſpiſhe in her wonted manner, euen loath to affoord me a good looke: am conſtrained, leſt I ſhould be of you and the worlde condemned, to take this poore occaſion to ſhew mine affectionate mind,
<pb facs="tcp:132660:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>not meaning thereby to make this a ſhew of a ſatisfaction for ſo great a debt, but onely in part in cutte off the conſuming intereſt, and to confeſſe vnto you in the witneſſe of the world a further duetie to bee accompliſhed. And knowing in parte the earneſt deſire you haue alwaies had; to ſee into forraine States, and acquaint your ſelfe with the diuers manners of nations. I finding here a wandering ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by chance, whom I perceiued fit to informe you of ſomewhat worthy the inquirie: hauing now procured him a poore Engliſh weede, I am bold to commend him vnto you, hoping you wil not deny him your friendly patronage, nor me your wonted fauour.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Yours wholly deuoted,</hi> Richard Sergier.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132660:33"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
